<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The vvhole and true discourse of the enterprises and secrete conspiracies that haue bene made against the person of Henry de Valois, most Christian king of Fraunce &amp; Poland Wherupon followed his death by the hand of a young Iacobin frier, the first day of August, 1589. Whereby the enemies of the Crown, thought to haue reduced &amp; brought all Fraunce to their will &amp; deuotion. Together with the assembly that the king before his death made of the princes of the blood, lordes and gentlemen that were in his armie, with the heads of the straungers, to whom he declared his last will. Englished out of the French copie, printed at Caan in Normandie</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1589</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 22 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 9 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A02963</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 13103</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S119798</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99855004</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99855004</idno>
            <idno type="VID">20474</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A02963)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 20474)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 569:15)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The vvhole and true discourse of the enterprises and secrete conspiracies that haue bene made against the person of Henry de Valois, most Christian king of Fraunce &amp; Poland Wherupon followed his death by the hand of a young Iacobin frier, the first day of August, 1589. Whereby the enemies of the Crown, thought to haue reduced &amp; brought all Fraunce to their will &amp; deuotion. Together with the assembly that the king before his death made of the princes of the blood, lordes and gentlemen that were in his armie, with the heads of the straungers, to whom he declared his last will. Englished out of the French copie, printed at Caan in Normandie</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[16] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Imprinted by Thomas Purfoote, and are to bee soulde at his shoppe without New-gate, ouer against S. sepulchers church,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London] :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1589.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Signatures: A-B⁴.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Bodleian Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Henry --  III, --  King of France, 1551-1589.</term>
               <term>Clément, Jacques, ca. 1567-1589.</term>
               <term>France --  History --  Henry III, 1574-1589 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-09</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-09</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-11</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-11</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:20474:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:20474:1"/>
            <p>THE VVhole and true Diſcourſe of the Enterpriſes and ſecrete Conſpiracies that haue bene made a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the perſon of Henry de Valois, moſt Chriſtian king of Fraunce &amp; Poland.</p>
            <p>VVherupon followed his death by the hand of a young Iacobin Frier, the firſt day of Auguſt, 1589. Whereby the e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemies of the Crown, thought to haue reduced &amp; brought all Fraunce to their will &amp; deuo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</p>
            <p>Together with the aſſembly that the king before his death made of the Princes of the blood; Lordes and Gentlemen that were in his Armie, with the heads of the ſtraungers, to whom he declared his laſt will.</p>
            <p>Engliſhed out of the French copie, printed at Caan in Normandie</p>
            <p>Imprinted by Thomas Purfoote, and are to bee ſoulde at his ſhoppe without New-gate, ouer againſt S. ſepulchers church, 1589.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="discourse">
            <pb facs="tcp:20474:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:20474:2"/>
            <head>
               <hi>The true diſcourſe of the</hi> enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terpriſe made againſt the Perſon of the late deceaſed King, wounded (wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of he dyed) by a yong Iacobin Frier, <hi>the firſt of this moneth of Auguſt 1589.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">Y</seg>F the holy ſcripture, yea God himſelfe, expreſſy forbid vs, (&amp; that with threat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning vs to fal into y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> indignatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> &amp; iugd<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t of the higher power) that we ſhould not in any wiſe couch or hurt the anoynted of the Lord: It is a matter worthy to bee wondred at, that hee (who calleth himſelfe the preacher of the goſpel) ſhould ſo far forget himſelf, as y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> he neither knewe nor vnderſtoode the will of God, who ſo greatly eſteemeth, and ordaineth to be honoured &amp; reſpected, the partie to whom hee committeth the the gouernment of a common weale: although he vſe rigoure and ſeueritie.</p>
            <p>And who (I pray you) from time out of mans memorie, can giue vs teſtimonie of ſo wretched an act, and ſo worthie of euerlaſting blame, to haue hapened, and to haue bene committed and perpetra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted in all chriſtiandome, as that which is yet all bloodie in our <hi>Fraunce,</hi> committed againſt our ſo gracious and mercifull King, <hi>Henrie de Valoys,</hi> King of <hi>Fraunce,</hi> and <hi>Polande?</hi> An act verily vt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terlie vnworthy a chriſtia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, &amp; that would not be be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leiued to haue bin exerciſed amongeſt the moſt bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>barous
<pb facs="tcp:20474:3"/>nations of the world.</p>
            <p>We find, yea in the holy ſcriptures themſelues, that there haue bine reuoultings, diſcontentme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts, contradictions, and murmurings, and that in the ende many people haue rayſed wars, againſt their kings and princes, by reaſon of the great ſubſidies impoſtes, and heauie burthens, and other charges that were layde vpon their ſhoulders very h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap> &amp; vneaſie to be borne. But it is not found that there hath an aſſault and murder ben done nor conſpired againſt the Soueraigne authoritie.</p>
            <p>Wee read of Salomon who had impoſed and layd vpon the backes of the people that were com<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>mitted vnto him by the authoritie of God, impor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table burdens wherewith the ſubiects felt them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> and wholy <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>reſſed. Ieroboam <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> welbeloued ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>r<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>imt, albeit he had receiued <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> by A<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>as the auncient prophet of God that <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> raigne <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> ten tribes of Iſraell, and that <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> but o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> of the tribes remaine in the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap>, yet the ſaid I<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>oboam being at <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> had rather <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>omon, and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> him. Not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="12 letters">
                  <desc>〈12 letters〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap>, and his <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> the kingdome, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> of the people was <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> when hee <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb facs="tcp:20474:3"/>ſupplication to the king, to eaſe them of thoſe hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uie burdens that his father had layde vppon them. Whereto king Roboam woulde not yeilde, and they went there waies very greatly diſcontenced. And the ſayd Ieroboam raigned ouer tenne of the tribes of Iſraeli: who crowned him kinge &amp; ruler ouer them. But they long continued not in that eſtate, but the vengeance of God fel vpon them af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter the death of the ſaide Roboam: And amongeſt all that is written of this goodly hiſtorie in the booke of Paralipomenon the <hi>13</hi> and <hi>14</hi> chapters, &amp; in the firſt booke of Kings, the <hi>1.2.3.4.</hi> &amp; other Chapters following, there is no mention made (though ther wanted no means of the peacuſing amongeſt them of any other meanes, nor of any o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther kinde of aſſaulting the king (though he were conſtrained to flie vnto Ieruſalem:) nor of Abias his ſonne that raigned after him. VVee finde alſo that in the warres many kings haue bene ſmitten &amp; ſlaine. Others alſo by the iuſt iudgment of God haue bene killed and wounded by diuerſe ſtraunge mortall woundes. The reuerence due to the king aſwell in the warres, as otherwiſe, hath bene and yet is in ſo great accoumpt, that there is an obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uation in the warres, when the King is there in perſon) to crie alowde: <hi>Saue the Kinge: faue the King.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>They will aledge, it was done vpon wrath and indignation, for that which was executed vpon <hi>Mounſire de Guyſe,</hi> by hys Maieſties commaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dement.</p>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:20474:4"/>I aunſweare them, it is not the part of a ſeruant nor of any other whomſoeuer to make himſelfe e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quall and euenlyke, nor to compare himſelfe with the authority, power, or highnes, of an Emperor, King, or Magiſtrace, who executeth and diſpoſeth of his affaires, as pleaſeth himſelf, and according to his good counſell. After whoſe example, and in imitation of hym, if perticuler perſons, ſhoulde take vpon them to make ordinaunces, and to enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>medle in the rule &amp; gouernment of the ciuil eſtate, &amp; the affaires of the kingdome. What order, what gouernment, what iuſtice, ſhould we haue therin<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> To whom might it be ſaid that the obedience were due, which we proteſt to yeild in the name of God, to our ſuperiours, whome he hath ordeined and e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtabliſhed ouer his people.</p>
            <p>There is no queſtion, nor controuerſie, but that a long time there hath bene verie ſecret practiſing againſt the king. For his maieſties owne ſelfe, hath often diſcouered verie euident tokens ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, whereby hee might eaſilie bee perſwaded, of their canckred hearts toward him. As may ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peare by the ſerching and ſifting that the houſe of Guize hath made, as being deſcended from Char<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lemaine, vpholding the Bulle of Pope Stephen, in the behalfe of Pepin king of <hi>Fraunce,</hi> and of his wife, with their two iſſues males, one of the which was the ſaide <hi>Charlemaine,</hi> the which bull (next after the conſecrating &amp; anoynting of the regality
<pb facs="tcp:20474:4"/>in the perſon of the ſaid Pepin and his wife, by the ſame Pope) conteinech a iudgme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t of curſe againſt them that ſhould preſume to enterpriſe the <hi>french ſcepter</hi> &amp; preuaile to obtaine the ſame, except they were ſuch as ſhould diſcend from the ſaid Pepin, &amp; his race. There haue ben other ſufficient occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s brought to light, which I will paſſe in ſilence.</p>
            <p>But I wonder why they laid that ſo long aſide, and oppoſed not themſelues, to them that haue raigned ſithencs that time. I wotte well that they haue ruled and gouerned in <hi>Fraunce</hi> in their time, and that nothing was done, but what they allowed for the moſt part.</p>
            <p>And to alleadge at this daie, that the king had hardely dealt with them: hee that had brought to light ſo many ſiniſter dealinges, and enterpri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, They indeuoring and purpoſing to aide and defend themſelues with a league and aſſocia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion (in a manner) of all the townes and commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nalties of all <hi>Fraunce,</hi> where they could get audi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence. This kinde of proceding was in truth con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluded and determined from the councel, of <hi>Trent:</hi> And being aſſured of a great number of people as well Churchmen, as Gentlemen, and of the thirde eſtate, vnder colour of the revniting of fayth and religion, and alſo of the aſſwaging and leſſening of the impoſitions taxes and ſubſidies that the kinge demanded by reaſon of the neceſſity of the affaires of his kingdome: and of other prankes, wherwith I may well ſay a great number of folke were be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>witched,
<pb facs="tcp:20474:5"/>forſaking their king, who onlye hath po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wer and authoritie in his kingdome to take order in all ſuch matters, the which people ſtayed them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues vpon certaine perticuler perſons, that haue not any meane to accompliſh the ſame, but only by taking their ſwordes in hande, and altogither to inforce the king to graunt to their minds, or elſe to conſtraine him to yeild vp his ſcepter: and intend<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ing thus to winne the authority that they ſeeke to haue ouer all <hi>Fraunce:</hi> to bring all things into con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſion and diſorder to murder all them that ſhould refuſe to bee obeidient to their will: to ſeaſe their goods and poſſeſſions, to recompence the heades of theſe warres, for their good ſeruice imployed for this league, at their coſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>es. Theſe matters are wel ynough knowne to many, by the actions that they haue co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mitted, yea &amp; after what ſort they haue led the kings maieſtie about, who for a certaine ſpace diſtruſted not their hipocriſie &amp; diſſimulation. But they could not ſo couertlye and cunningly playe their game, but it was eſpyed, how they had deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berated, to ſhutte the king vp in a religious houſe, there to finiſh the reſt of his dayes.</p>
            <p>Now when this confederacie and league was thus confirmed and ſetled, and the time of the exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cution of their intent drewe neere, wee know howe the kinge was conſtrained to withdrawe himſelfe from <hi>Paris,</hi> and all thoſe matters that enſued ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vppon, vntill the aſſembly of his generall eſtats at <hi>Bloys.</hi> At which-place, in the beginning, the king
<pb facs="tcp:20474:5"/>of <hi>Nauarra,</hi> and all thoſe of his race, are declared to be vomcet and vncapable to ſucceed, to the crowne <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>Fraunce,</hi> as men attainted &amp; conuicted of hereſie in their onely iudgement, with confiſcation of all their poſſeſſians. In which place they thought ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ryly to haue accompliſhed and attained to the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection of their ſecret intents and complots. But when matters ſtirred and turned otherwiſe then they expected, and the eſtates ceaſed: They muſt needes open the cloſet of their heartes, whereby were reuealed their fautors and aſſuters. And e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen as there was left but one tribe of the children of Iſraell in the houſe of Dauid, in the handes of king Roboam, the lawfull and naturall ſonne, and rightfull ſucceſſor of his father Salomon: ſo did the king finde himſelfe ſtripped of all his good townes, noble men, and an infinit number of men at armes, ſo that he had no ſure acceſſe nor place of retrait, ſauing in the leſſer part of his kingdom, though there were many of his ſide in the prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant townes, but the force was not in their hands. Seeing themſelues then thus ſtrong, they cried. <hi>God ſaue the League, God ſaue the League,</hi> The which word, beeauſe it ſeemed odious, they haue changed into <hi>Vnion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The king weighing and conſidering this kinde of proceeding, and perceuuing their demeanors, pride and ambition, ſetling &amp; tooting in the harles of theſe bypocrites, the taking of his townes, bor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roughes, caſtels, and ſtrong holdes, with double aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuranes
<pb facs="tcp:20474:6"/>of men in pay, and out of pay: it was <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>ſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>farie for him to craue aid els where, and as he was alwaies well aſſured of the good will of the ki<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> of <hi>Nauarra</hi> his brother in Law, toward him, ſo did <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e not ſticke, nor make any difficultie to call him to his aide: Whereto the ſaid Lord would not in any re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect diſobey: notwithſtanding the rigour of the e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicts and declarations that the ſaid king of <hi>Fraunce</hi> had made againſt my ſaid Lord the king of <hi>Naurra</hi> and his alders, and had cauſed their goods and poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſions both mouable and vnmouable to bee ſolde, acording to the deſire of his enemies the leaguers, beſides other matters which they cauſed the ſayde deceaſed king to doe by force, for the moſt part, and wherein moſt often hee knew not what hee did. Which matters the ſaid Lord the king of <hi>Nauarra</hi> hath ſufficientite ſet downe at large in all his pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtations that he hath made to his Maieſtie.</p>
            <p>Now Sathan, ſeeking like a roaring lion who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> be may deuour, perceiuing this good and holie <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greement and reconciliation, with the good will of the faithfull proteſtantes of the kings ſide, he could no longer ſtay him ſelfe in aſſurance, foraſmuch as his deuiſes went euill forward. For theſe of the kinges ſide, taking courage, haue brought ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie ſheept backe againe to their owne fold. Here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withall, he perceiued howe the ſtraunger tooke the cauſe in hand, and ſtirred againſt the diſturbers of the tranquilitie. They coulde not other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e iudge, for the behoof of the cauſe, but to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecute
<pb facs="tcp:20474:6"/>the head that the me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>bers might be y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ſteker</p>
            <p>In this iudgment and opinion, there bee many ſortes of folke. For ſome of them ought to bee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaine and continent in their willes: Others are holde and ignorant, ledde by their owne affection without iudgment: Other ſome contrarie to their ſolitarines, are forerunners: who contrarie to their profeſſion, entermeddle to doe things cleane contrarie to all honeſt conuerſation, which cauſeth them to be euill liked, of ſuch as deſire to walke plainlie in their vocation. All the which kindes of folke thus put together, cannot in their particular paſſions, which are without all holines and pietie, rightly nor fitly giue any good counſell for ſuch matters as are to be done: for they prefer their wicked intention which is tranſported with pride and vnſaciable conuetouſnes) before all good affe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, and the ſaftie of the common weale. And all of them ſo put together, without foreſight of that which is to come, reiecting al ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ner of know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of God, cannot deliverate any other thing ſauing onely the cutting away of the head of the tree, that the braunches might wither away the ſooner.</p>
            <p>This Counſell was holden at Paris, whereat were preſent at that time the principall heads of this league, in which place, Sathan offered one worſe then Iudas, for Iudas kiſſed his maiſter af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter be had ſold him, and acknowledged his offence afterwards. But this yong man, a Iacobin Frier
<pb facs="tcp:20474:7"/>of religion, hath made no difficulty nor ſticking, to wound to death him, that ſo hartily loued y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> order aboue all the whole nations of religious perſons, who had cheriſhed the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, as they that were welcome about his perſon. This will I ſay, it is no nouel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie that they begin to doe euill: I will produce an Emperour that was poyſoned by a halowed <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>aſt, empoiſoned notwithſtanding, which was preſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted vnto him by a Iacobin. This order of Friers preachers haue alwaies bene very deſirous to bee welcome amongeſt men of high calling, and to vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dertake odious offices, as to be of the inquyſition of fayth and others. Theſe of the League, vpon conſideration thereof, prouoke and ſtyrre more and more, thys poore curſed wretch, within whoſe hart Sathan lodged; to keepe, him alwaies in this curſed mind. Upon the reſolution hereof, they pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pared him a knife for this purpoſe; which they dou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble poiſoned with ſuch kind of poyſon, that though the party ſtryken with thys Inſtrument dye not preſentlie yet it ſhall not be poſſible for him to e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcape, nor liue long after.</p>
            <p>Vpon tueſday the firſt of Auguſt, very early in the morning, this diueliſh perſon, taketh his ior<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney, purpeſing to find his Maieſty at S. Clou, two ſmall leagnes from Paris: Attending his vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>r<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſing, for feare of l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſing the occaſion to ſpeake with him: being well aſſured to haue entrance to him, in reſpect of the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>auour that the king bore vnto them: hauing in his hand a letter or miſſiue to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liuer
<pb facs="tcp:20474:7"/>liuer vnto him from the firſt preſident of Paris, as the report goeth, whom they detaine priſoner.</p>
            <p>Aſſoone as he was aduerciſed that he might co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueniently ſpeake with the king, he entereth with a bolde face, as hardy as a lyon, and like a bloody traitor gaue him the <hi>Iubé</hi> with a very low &amp; hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble curteſie, offering vnto him the ſaid pretended writing of the ſame Preſident, and comming neer to his Maieſtie, he ſignified vnto him how bee had another ſecret to declare vnto him. The king hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring the ſame, cauſed two Gentlemen to goe out, that ſerued him at his vpriſing. Then this Iaco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bin co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tinuing in his wicked mind, drew this knife and therewith thruſt the king into the litle belly as they call it: the which ſtrok entred not into his body, neyther dyed he preſentlie. The king ſeeing this, and being mooued, laid hold of a dagger that lay neere vnto hym, and therwith ſtroke the ſayd Monke, who being hurt with the ſtroke, and much affrighted, fell preſently down for feare: Howbeit not dead, but as is commonly ſene, a malefactor is neuer ſetled and aſſured in conſcience when he go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth about to e<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ecute ſuch a crueltie. Thys wret<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched Monke, being worſe feared, then hurt, had leyſure to ſpeake.</p>
            <p>Vpon the which noiſe, the ſaid gentlemen ſoden<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly came in againe with others, who by the kings co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mandement, ſlue him not, but tooke him vp. Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter the king w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s dreſſed, euen ſo far that hee had ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen ſtitches with a needle, as the report goeth, he
<pb facs="tcp:20474:8"/>gaue co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mandement for the examination of the ſaide Monke, which was accompliſhed, and be declares who ſet him on, the authors, and all other informa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, with his name, and vocation, &amp; that he was not counterfayted, but of the ſayd order. Which being finiſhed, through impatiency he was kylled, ſuffering aboue a hundred thruſts with daggers, &amp; which is worthy the maruayling at, it is reported that the ſayd Monks fleſh became as blacke as a very rauen, which ys eaſie to be beleeued, becauſe Sathan dwelt wythin hym, and then the Iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of god that appeareth to men in diuerſe ſorts: behold here a pytyfull tragedy.</p>
            <p>But as God will ſerue his purpoſe with men, by many and diuerſe ſortes, the king being yet of good there, with the hope which hee had conceiued that his wound might mend, ſent with ſpeede, for his brother in lawe the king of <hi>Nauarra,</hi> the lordes of his Court. Gouernours, Captaines that were in his armye, &amp; ſpecially the heads of the ſtraung<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers that were in his countrie, to the intent that if it ſo fell out that hee died, the diſorder and miſrule ſhould not be ſo great, that all the army ſhould be broken vp, no<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> an vnmeaſurable confuſion enſue therevpon. When they were all thus aſſembled, God put into the kings mouth ſo ſtedfaſt and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> ſpeach, as though he had felt noe griefe, and began to ſignify to the aſſemblie: hat the lawful ſucceſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the royall eſtate of <hi>Fraunce,</hi> fell not to anye o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, ſauing in the perſon of <hi>Barbon,</hi> and declaring
<pb facs="tcp:20474:8"/>at that time the kinge of <hi>Nauarra</hi> firſt ſucceſſor, he prayed and exhorted the whole companie ſo to ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge him, and to be fayth full vnto him: and to proteſt all with one voice the acknowledging &amp; taking in good part of this deede, and true obedy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, as to the true and lawfull heire, and to cauſe the like promiſe &amp; acknowledgment to bee made in the campe by all true and faithfull Captaines and ſouldiers that could not bee preſent at the ſayde aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſembly, aſwell naturall frenchmen as ſtraungers, who all with gladnes of hart (though otherwiſe ſad and ſorowfull for his maieſties wound) ſwore to execute the kinges will.</p>
            <p>Vpon the ordering and diſpoſing of all matters in this ſorte, the kinge ſent letters into all places, where he had yet the full gouernment, &amp; eſpecially to <hi>Caan</hi> to <hi>Mounſyr de la verune Gouernour and Baylly at Caan,</hi> and to the court of parliament eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſhed at the ſayd place, with hope, that there was no daunger of death. Aſmuch was written vnto them from <hi>Mounſyr de Mountpenſier Gouernour general</hi> for his maieſtie in <hi>Norma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dy,</hi> who was the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> at <hi>Andely</hi> vpon the riuer of <hi>Seyne,</hi> where becauſed his whole armie to take the like oathe: exhortinge the heades to maintaine the kings will. Whiche was accorded vnto him, with hope as the ſaid lord gouernor demed, that there ſhold be no daunger of the kings death, by Gods helpe.</p>
            <p>But the next daie following, the ſaid lord gouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nor chaunged that kind of language, writing to the
<pb facs="tcp:20474:9"/>ſayd Bayly of <hi>Caan,</hi> whereby he gaue him to vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtande how the king dyed the wedneſdaye next following the date wherein he was wounded.</p>
            <p>An aſſembly was holden at <hi>Caan</hi> vpon ſonday the ſixt day of Auguſt, of all the Citizens and In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>habitantes of the ſame place, in the preſence of the Bayly of <hi>Caan,</hi> and the Court of Parliament, the bodie of the towne, and the gentlemen of the coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trie, where the ſkilful perſon <hi>Mounſeur de Liſores,</hi> Preſide<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t in the ſaid court of Parliament, did ſit as Preſident, and when he had deliuered and ſhewed to al the whole company what matters had happe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, with admiration of the ſpeach of thys Lord, as proteſting perfect loyalty on his owne behalfe: publication of his Maieſties letters and of Mou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penſiers letters was publiquely made, where all vniformally ſware their acknowledgment &amp; fide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity, euery man proteſting to mayntayne the will of Henry <hi>de Valoys</hi> thus deceaſed, in all thinges that it conteineth.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:20474:9"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
